Finding Aid for National Organization for Women, Oakland County Chapter Records 1978-2002
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
National Organization for Women, Oakland County Chapter Records 1978-2002
National Organization for Women. Oakland County Chapter.
Administrative files include minutes, membership materials, and newsletters. Topical concern activities and relationship with Michigan NOW and other state NOW chapters.
0222 Bj 2
1 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The materials were donated by the Oakland County NOW in December 2001 (Donor No. 8608 ). Additional materials were received in 2003.
The record group is open for research.
The Oakland County chapter of the National Organization for Women was started in September of 1973 by a nucleus of Detroit NOW members to address local issues of interest to women. The Oakland County NOW was the sixteenth NOW chapter to be formed in Michigan and held its first meeting on September 25, 1974, with the attendance of over 150 women. The North Oakland/Oakland University NOW merged with the Oakland County NOW in October 1991, making the Oakland County NOW the largest chapter in the state at that time. Oakland County NOW marked its 25th anniversary in November 1998.
The Oakland County NOW's purpose is "to take action to bring women into full participation in American society now, exercising all the rights, privileges and responsibilities thereof." The chapter "opposes discrimination against women everywhere." Oakland County NOW sponsors local events promoting these purposes and joins with other chapters in exacting further political action.
These records include the papers of a number of Oakland County NOW officers, particularly those of Judy Burgess, who served as Oakland County NOW's recording secretary from 1996 to 1999 and as president from 2001. Because the organization is largely volunteer-driven, the records are by no means comprehensive, and are limited to the materials produced by and/or received by the officers who donated the records. The collection is organized into two series: administrative files and topical files.
Subjects:
National Organization for Women. Oakland County Chapter.; Feminism--Michigan--Oakland County.; National Organization for Women. Michigan Conference.; Oakland County (Mich.); Women's rights--Michigan.
- Administrative Files
  The bulk of the collection consists of chapter newsletters in the administrative files series (3 folders). These chapter newsletters are the cornerstone of the collection, reflecting the chapter's activities across almost two decades -- from 1983 to 2002. Not only do the newsletters paint a picture of the chapter's activities, they also provide a glimpse into national and state affairs of interest to the Oakland County NOW.
  - Agendas and Minutes, Board of Directors Meetings 1983-2002 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Agendas and Minutes, Chapter Meetings 1982-2002 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Annual Report 1993 (Box 1)
  - Attendance Records 1989-1995 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Bylaws 1992, 1990, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1984-2001 (to/from politicians, with members, etc., scattered) (Box 1)
  - Events 1982-2002 (programs, fliers, advertisements of events) (Box 1)
  - Leadership List 1996-1997, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Membership Materials (Box 1)
  - Membership Rosters 1991-1993 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - News Clippings (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1983-2002 scattered, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets Regarding Pregnancy 1978-1981 (Box 1)
  - Treasurers Reports 1985-1987, 1996 (scattered) (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The topical files series is rather thin, but does provide further detail of some of the chapter's activities and provides information about areas of interest to the organization. The Michigan NOW grouping includes newsletters, state membership renewal reports, describing the enrollment of all of the state chapters; other chapter's newsletters provide information about the activities of other Michigan NOW chapters and provide a comparative context for the Oakland County NOW activities.
  - Abortion -- Bogus Clinics 1985 (Box 1)
  - Abortion --; Right to Life circa 1990 (Box 1)
  - Hotline 1986-1988, 1990-1992, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Lesbian and Gay Rights 1986-1993 (Box 1)
  - March For Women's Lives April 5, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Michigan NOW
    - By-Laws 1994 (Box 1)
    - Education Task Force 1989-1993 (Box 1)
    - Homemakers Rights Task Force (Box 1)
    - Membership Renewal Reports 1986, 1992-1994 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters 1993-2003 (Box 1)
    - Sexual Assault Guide Book for Oakland County 1983 (Box 1)
    - Officer Nominations (Box 1)
    - State Conferences
      - May 1992 (Box 1)
      - May 1993 (Box 1)
      - May 1994 (Box 1)
      - April 1998 (Box 1)
      - May 1999 (Box 1)
      - June 2000 (Box 1)
      - June 2001 (Box 1)
      - April 2002 (Box 1)
    - State Coordinating Council Meetings
      - March 19, 1988 (Box 1)
      - January 23, 1993 (Box 1)
      - March 27, 1993 (Box 1)
      - September 18, 1993 (Box 1)
      - November 13, 1993 (Box 1)
      - January 22, 1994 (Box 1)
      - March 19, 1994 (Box 1)
      - November 5, 1994 (Box 1)
      - September 23, 1995 (Box 1)
      - March 23, 1996 (Box 1)
      - September 13, 1997 (Box 1)
      - September 16, 2000 (Box 1)
      - March 17, 2001 (Box 1)
      - September 15, 2001 (Box 1)
      - November 17, 2001 (Box 1)
      - January 26, 2002 (Box 1)
      - June 29, 2002 (Box 1)
      - October 12, 2002 (Box 1)
  - Other Chapters' Newsletters
    - Detroit 1992-1994 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Downriver 1989-1992 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Kalamazoo 1992-1993 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Macomb County 1986-1994 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - North Oakland 1986-1991 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Northern 1991-1992 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Saginaw 1992 (Box 1)
    - Western Wayne 1993-2001 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Phone Banking (Box 1)
  - Racial Diversity 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Win With Women September 17, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Women's Equity Day August 15, 1990 (Box 1)